{
  "reference_number": "8386",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The Government needs to set a clear target. Delay and uncertainty need to be minimised."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Deep cuts are needed for all greenhouse gases. The sooner this happens the better. It will be more economic in the long term and\n the sooner cuts start the lower overall greenhouse gas quantities will be globally. Also, reducing short-lived greenhouse gases may\n\n be an essential tool if there is a need to rapidly reduce the gases as critical climate tipping points are approached. Stabilisation would\n not be helpful in this situation."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "The NZ ETS has been abused in the past. This should not be allowed to happen again. We need to make meaningful reductions by\n\n cutting our domestic emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but with provisos. Changes should only be to strengthen the target, not to weaken it. There will be a lot of pressure on\n government to water down the goals, to delay and to do nothing and a future government may be tempted to do this. This must be\n avoided at all costs. We must keep on target or do better. Targets need to be binding."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This will provide clarity, certainty and a clear message that this is important. People, businesses and communities will be able to make\n decisions as a result."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "Reviews should not be used to abuse the process. Once again, they should only be used to strengthen targets, not weaken them.\n\n This fits with the Paris Agreement requirement to maintain or strengthen goals ever five years."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Once again, the government should have the ability to ratchet up the goals, not to weaken them."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Without this it will be too easy for governments which are less committed to the required goals, to procrastinate or pretend to be\ndoing something when they are actually not."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Important issues to consider are that goals are suitably ambitious and consistent with climate science. They must follow the\nrequirements of the Paris Agreement. Major cuts need to be made over the next decade, with delay only making it much harder to\n\narrive at our ultimate goal (zero carbon). Fairness and equity are important issues. Vulnerable communities will need protection, as will\nneighbouring Pacific Island nations which will require on-going support as sea levels rise. Fairness also means that all sectors will\n\nneed to take part (agriculture should not be exempt). The principles of te Tiriti o Waitangi must be respected."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "I have suggested that there should be no reliance on trading schemes. I feel that New Zealand should be making its contribution by\n\nactually making real cuts in domestic emissions. If there is an ETS, then the Climate Change Commission should have an advisory\nrole."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is important that the Commission has an appropriate range of experts. They should not be political appointees who have an\nideological viewpoint that suits a particular government."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation strategies should in no way weaken the commitment to the reduction of greenhouse gases, which must always be the\nfirst priority."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "There is a need to minimise the government's ability to ignore or deviate from the Climate Commission advice. The government must\njustify any deviations within a certain time-frame. The Commission's advice needs to have teeth."
    }
  ]
}
